a diffraction gradient has 5000 lines
per centimeter
calculate the second order angle if a
wavelength of 650 nanometers is used as
a light source
so first what exactly is a diffraction
gradient
it's basically
very similar to young's double slit
experiment but with many slits
in fact there's
five thousand slits per centimeter
now the interference pattern will be the
same
in a sense that
we're going to have a bright fringe
at the center
now these maximums these bright fringes
they're very sharp and narrow
now this is good for measuring the
wavelength of
a light source
and so we're going to get these very
sharp peaks
above and below the central peak
so here m is 0
and here m is 1 and 2 and so forth so
this is going to be theta 1
and here we have theta 2 the second
order angle
and below m is negative 1 negative 2
and d is the distance
or the width of each slit
and l is the distance between the screen
and the diffraction gradient
now the diffraction gradient has slits
that are equally spaced and parallel to
each other
and so machine can be used to
create all of these
slits
within a very small
space there's five thousands list per
centimeter so
they're very close to each other each
slit is very very small
the main formula that we need to use is
this equation
d sine theta
is equal to m times lambda
now d is equal to one over n
where n represents the number of lines
per meter
so let's calculate this thing first
so the diffraction gradient has 5000
lines
per centimeter and let's convert
centimeters to meters there's 100
centimeters per meter
and so we could cancel these two
and so 5000
times a hundred
is five hundred thousand
which we could say it's five times ten
to five
lines per meter
so d is going to be one over n so that's
one divided by
five times ten to the five
and so this is equal to two times ten to
the minus six
meters per line
so that's the spacing
of each slit in this problem
so now that we have d we can calculate
everything else
so let's make a list of what we know
so the second order angle theta 2
is what we're looking for
lambda is 650 nanometers
and because we're dealing with a second
order angle m is two
so let's plug in everything into this
equation
so d is two times ten to the minus six
times sine of theta two
m is two and lambda is six 650
times 10 to the minus 9.
so let's take 2 and multiply by 650
times 10 to the negative 9
and then divide that by 2 times 10 to
the minus 6.
so we get that sine of theta 2
is 0.65
so theta 2 is going to be arc sine
of 0.65 or the inverse sine function
and so the answer is 40.5 degrees
so that's the second order angle
for this diffraction gradient
if we use a wavelength of 650 nanometers
number two
a diffraction gradient has ten thousand
lines per centimeter
if the third order bright fringe
has an angle of 25 degrees
what is the wavelength of the light
source
so based on the last example feel free
to pause the video and work on this one
so let's start with
okay let's redo that let's start with 10
000 lines per centimeter
and let's convert centimeters to meters
just like we did before
so one meter is equal to 100 centimeters
and so 10 000 times 100 is a million
which is the same as 1 times 10 to the 6
lines per meter
now d is equal to 1 over n
and this quantity is equal to n
so d is going to be one divided by one
times ten to the sixth
which is one times ten to the negative
six
and we're going to flip the units so
it's going to be meters
per line
so that's the spacing
of each slit
so now
let's make a list of what else we know
so the third order angle
is 25 degrees
and so m has to be three
our goal is to calculate the wavelength
so let's use the formula d sine theta
is equal to m times lambda
so d is one times ten to the minus six
and then it's going to be times sine of
25 degrees
that's equal to three times lambda
so let's multiply 1 times 10 to the
minus 6 by sine 25
and then divide that result by 3.
so the wavelength is 1.4
1 times ten to the negative seven
meters
now let's convert this to nanometers
so one nanometer is one times ten to the
negative nine
meters
so we need to take 1.41 times 10 to the
minus 7
and divided by 10 to the negative 9.
and so the wavelength is 141
nanometers
so this is the answer to the problem
number three
the second order bright fringe
has an angle of 18 degrees
using a light source with a wavelength
of 540 nanometers
how many lines per centimeter
does the diffraction gradient have
so what do you think we need to do in
this problem
go ahead and work on it
so let's make a list of what we know
so the second order bright fringe
or the second order angle
is 18 degrees
the wavelength is 540 nanometers
now because the subscript is 2
we know that m is equal to 2.
so if we can calculate d
we can then calculate the number of
lines per centimeter
so let's use this equation d sine theta
is equal to m times lambda
so theta is 18 degrees
m is 2 and lambda is 540
times 10 to the negative 9.
so let's multiply those two numbers
first
and so that's going to be 1.08
times 10 to negative 6.
now let's divide both sides by
sine of 18 degrees
and so now we have d which is three
point four nine
five times ten to the minus six
and the units
is going to be meters per line
now we said that d
is equal to one divided by n
that means n
is one over d
so that's gonna be one divided by
three point four nine five
times ten to the minus six
or take your previous answer
and just raise it to the negative one
power
and so n
is going to be 286 thousand
and the units will be lines per meter
so now all we need to do is convert
meters into centimeters
and we'll get this answer
now one meter is equal to a hundred
centimeters
so this time
we need to divide by a hundred
and so this particular diffraction
gradient
has 2861
lines per centimeter
and so that's the answer for this
problem
you